Guide to the Vincent J. Fontana Collection of "Thank You" Letters 1953-2005 MS 3222
New-York Historical Society
Vincent J. Fontana collection of "thank you" letters
1953-2005
New-York Historical Society
Fontana, Vincent J.
MS 3222
0.209 Linear feet in 1 half document box.
A collection of letters from notable individuals written to Dr. Vincent J. Fontana (1923–2005), longtime medical director of the New York Foundling Hospital, thanking him for services rendered or for sending them one of his books, such as "Somewhere a Child is Crying: Maltreatment—Causes and Prevention." Writers include actor Rosie O'Donnell; philanthropist Brooke Astor; New York City mayors John V. Lindsay and Abraham D. Beame; President Jimmy Carter and First Lady Barbara Bush; and Francis Spellman and Terrence J. Cooke, Cardinals, Archbishops of New York.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult it, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lee Bobrow (sister of Dr. Fontana), 2016.
Arrangement
The letters are filed alphabetically by the writer's surname. Multiple letters from the same writer are filed chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
An authority on child welfare, and author of such seminal texts as "The Maltreated Child: The Maltreatment Syndrome in Children: A Medical, Legal and Social Guide," Dr. Vincent J. Fontana (1923–2005) was the longtime medical director of the New York Foundling Hospital, and its associated, eponymous Vincent J. Fontana Center for Child Protection. Fontana chaired the Mayor's Task Force on Child Abuse and Neglect during the administrations of John V. Lindsay, Abraham D. Beame, and Edward I. Koch. Prior to his pediatric work, he served as personal physician to President Dwight D. Eisenhower and Francis, Cardinal Spellman, Archbishop of New York. [For further information, see "Dr. Vincent Fontana, 81, Voice for Abused Children, Dies," in The New York Times, July 9, 2005.]
Scope and Contents
While some letters in the collection thank Dr. Fontana for medical services rendered, others acknowledge receipt of one or another of his books, such as "Somewhere a Child is Crying: Maltreatment—Causes and Prevention" (1973, 1983), or "Save the Family, Save the Child: What We Can Do To Help Children At Risk" (1991). The following list of notable letter writers reflects Dr. Fontana's wide-reaching correspondence in the pursuit of medicine and child welfare:
Arts & entertainment: Paul Anka (b. 1941), singer; Rita Gam (1926–2016), actor; Polly Holliday (b. 1937), actor; Joseph E. Levine (1905–1987), film producer; Loretta Lynn (1932–2022), singer; Rosie O'Donnell (b. 1962), actor; Harold "Hal" Prince (1928–2019), theater director; Bryan Robertson (1925–2002), English curator and arts manager; Ned Rorem (1923–2022), composer; Maria Jeritza Seery (1887–1982), soprano; Peter Yarrow (b. 1938), singer.
Child welfare & philanthropy: Mrs. Vincent (Brooke) Astor (1902–2007), philanthropist; Eric Brettschneider, now Acting Commissioner for the NYC Administration for Children's Services; Elbridge T. Gerry Jr., New York Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children; Dr. C. Henry Kempe (1922–1984) pediatrician, first in the medical community to recognize "child abuse"; Sara O'Meara and Yvonne Fedderson, founders, Childhelp USA.
Diplomats: Giovanni Benelli (1921–1982), Substitute for General Affairs, Vatican; Maxwell M. Rabb (1910–2002), U.S. Ambassador to Italy; John A. Volpe (1908–1994), U.S. Ambassador to Italy.
Educators: Joseph T. Cahill (1919–2003), President, St. John's University; Donald J. Harrington (b. 1945), President, St. John's University; John C. Sawhill (1936–2000), President, New York University; Joseph Shenker (1939–2008), President, Bank Street College of Education.
Mayors of New York: Abraham D. Beame (1906–2001); Rudolph W. Giuliani (b. 1944); Edward I. Koch (1924–2013); John V. Lindsay (1921–2000).
Elected officials & political figures: Robert B. Anderson (1910–1989), U.S. Secretary of the Navy, U.S. Secretary of the Treasury; Mario Biaggi (1917–2015), U.S. House of Representatives from New York; Arthur F. Burns (1904–1987), Chairman, Federal Reserve; Barbara Bush (1925–2018), First Lady; Jimmy Carter (b. 1924), U.S. President; John R. Crews (1894–1975), Chairman, Kings County Republican County Committee; Mario M. Cuomo (1932–2015), Governor of New York; Matilda Cuomo (b. 1931), First Lady of New York; John H. Dillon, Administrative Assistant to the Secretary of the Navy; Thomas K. Duane (b. 1955), New York State Senator; Perry B. Duryea Jr. (1921–2004), New York State Assembly member; Thomas C. Hennings Jr. (1903–1960), U.S. Senate; J. Edgar Hoover (1895–1972), F.B.I. director; Walter F. Mondale (1928–2021), U.S. Vice President; Robert M. Morgenthau (1919–1919), District Attorney, County of New York; Richard Nixon (1913–1994), as former U.S. Vice President; Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis (1929–1994), former First Lady; Cesar A. Perales (b. 1940), Commissioner, State of New York Department of Social Services, later New York Secretary of State; Janet Reno (1938–2016), U.S. Attorney General; Nelson A. Rockefeller (1908–1979), Governor of New York, U.S. Vice President; Fred A. Seaton (1909–1974), U.S. Secretary of the Interior; Charles Thomas (1897–1983), U.S. Secretary of the Navy; Ann C. Whitman (1908–1991), Personal Secretary to President Eisenhower.
Religious leaders: Patrick V. Ahern (1919–2011), Auxiliary Bishop of New York; Terrence J. Cooke (1921–1983), Cardinal, Archbishop of New York; John O'Connor (1920–2000), Cardinal, Archbishop of New York; Paul VI, Pope (1897–1978); Francis Spellman (1889–1967), Cardinal, Archbishop of New York.
Autographs.; Letters (correspondence); Celebrities.; Child welfare -- New York (State) -- New York.; Pediatricians.; Politicians.; Religious leaders.; Signatures (Writing); Fontana, Vincent J.; New York Foundling Hospital
- Vincent J. Fontana collection of "thank you" letters, 1953-2005
  - "Thank you" letters: "A", 1957–2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Letters from
    • Patrick V. Ahern (2000 May 11)
    • Robert B. Anderson (1954 March 16; 1957 June 13; 1961 Sept. 7; 1971 June 17)
    • Paul Anka (autographed photo, n.d.)
    • Mrs. Vincent (Brooke) Astor (1997 Jan. 10)
  - "Thank you" letters: "B", 1954–1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    • Abraham D. Beame (1974 Dec. 16 + photo of swearing in; 1977 Aug. 16)
    • J. [Giovanni] Benelli (1974 March 6, + photocopy)
    • Mario Biaggi (1973 July 18, Oct. 4, Nov. 26; 1974 Dec. 26; 1977 Jan. 4)
    • Eric Brettschneider (1997 Nov. 12)
    • Arthur F. Burns (1954 July 26; 1969 Feb. 7; 1973 Nov. 7)
    • Barbara Bush (1992 Feb. 10)
  - "Thank you" letters: "C", 1966–1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    • Rev. Joseph T. Cahill (1976 Jan. 22 + copies of 2 awards; 1982 Sept. 27)
    • Jimmy Carter (1980 Feb. 13)
    • John R. Crews (1954 March 4 + photo of Fontana with General "Wild Bill" Donovan, American Ambassador to Thailand)
    • Terrence J. Cooke (1966 Dec. 30; 1968 Feb. 21 + photocopy, March 7; 1969 Feb. 20, Oct. 21, Dec. 14; 1973 Oct. 15; 1976 Sept. 3, Nov. 23; 1977 Feb. 23, Apr. 30, July 7, Oct. 17; 1978 Jan. 23)
    • Mario M. Cuomo (1990 Oct. 19, photocopy)
    • Matilda Cuomo (1983 April 11; 1992 Feb. 27)
  - "Thank you" letters: "D", 1954–1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    • John H. Dillon (1954 Nov. 17)
    • Thomas K. Duane (1999 Oct. 28)
    • Perry B. Duryea Jr. (1978 Nov. 28)
  - "Thank you" letters: "F", 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter from Blanche and Philip Fried (1995 Jan. 28)
  - "Thank you" letters: "G", 1988–2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    • Rita Gam (1988 [Nov.?] 5)
    • Elbridge T. Gerry Jr. (2000 April 26)
    • Rudolph W. Giuliani (1991 April 18)
  - "Thank you" letters: "H", 1953–2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    • Donald J. Harrington (2005 Feb. 14)
    • Thomas C. Hennings Jr. (1955 Jan. 21)
    • Polly Holliday (autographed photo, in character as "Flo" from sitcom "Alice," n.d.)
    • J. Edgar Hoover (1953 July 22)
  - "Thank you" letters: "K", 1978–1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    • Dr. C. Henry Kempe (n.d.)
    • Edward I. Koch (1978 Aug. 4; 1987 Sept. 11; + 2 photographs)
  - "Thank you" letters: "L", 1967–1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    • Joseph E. Levine (1971 Sept. 10; 1976 May 13)
    • John V. Lindsay (1967 April 21; 1968 Sept. 4, Dec. 11; 1971 Jan. 7; June 14)
    • Loretta Lynn (n.d. + photo)
  - "Thank you" letters: "M", 1973–2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    • Walter F. Mondale (1973 July 24 [photocopy]; 1973 Sept. 10)
    • Robert M. Morgenthau (1995 July 27; 2000 May 25; 2003 April 15)
  - "Thank you" letters: "N", 1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Letter from Richard Nixon (1961 Sept. 11)
  - "Thank you" letters: "O", 1971–2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    • John O'Connor (1998 Nov. 10)
    • Rosie O'Donnell (1997 Oct. 8)
    • Sara O'Meara and Yvonne Fedderson (2000 Nov. 9)
    • Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis (1971 Dec. 17)
  - "Thank you" letters: "P", 1963–2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    • Pope Paul VI (prayer card, 1963)
    • Cesar A. Perales (1983 May 20)
    • Harold Prince (2002 June 19)
  - "Thank you" letters: "R", 1954–1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    • Maxwell M. Rabb (1954 Nov. 13; 1956 April 25; 1982 March 8 + clipping in Italian)
    • Janet Reno (1993 Aug. 27)
    • Bryan Robertson (1970 Jan. 28)
    • Nelson A. Rockefeller (1973 Oct. 26)
    • Ned Rorem (notecard + program, n.d.)
  - "Thank you" letters: "S", 1954–1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    • John C. Sawhill (1976 June 30)
    • Fred A. Seaton (1957 April 10)
    • Maria Jeritza Seery (1971 Feb. 22)
    • Joseph Shenker (1995 Jan. 11)
    • Francis Spellman (1954 Dec. 16; 1957 Oct. 2; 1966 Oct. 21)
  - "Thank you" letters: "T", 1954 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    Letter from Charles Thomas (1954 Nov. 21)
  - "Thank you" letters: "V", 1976–1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Letters from John A. Volpe (1976 Jan. 19; 1983 May 4; 1984 Feb. 27)
  - "Thank you" letters: "W", 1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter from Ann C. Whitman (1960 May 26)
  - "Thank you" letters: "Y", 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    Letter from Peter Yarrow (1992 May 24)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1955-2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes letters from unidentified writers, invitations, photographs, clippings, etc.
  - Photographs of Dr. Fontana with children, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    Spiral-bound compilation.